Guide to the Stephen Facey Collection on Theatre Genesis MSS.595
Fales Library and Special Collections
Stephen Facey Collection on Theatre Genesis
1964-1978
1964-2016
Fales Library and Special Collections
Facey, Stephen
Theatre Genesis
MSS.595
4.25 linear feet in 8 manuscript boxes in 1 half manuscript box
2 sound tape reels
Stephen Facey is a trustee of Movement Research, The Chocolate Factory Theater, the St. Mark's Historic Landmark Fund, and the New York Preservation Archive Project. He served as the Parish Administrator of St. Mark's Church In-the-Bowery, where he managed the church's Arts Projects, comprised of Theatre Genesis, The Poetry Project, The Film Project, and Danspace. The Stephen Facey Collection on Theatre Genesis (dated 1964-2016) consists of materials collected by Facey documenting the history and activities of the off-off-Broadway theater Theatre Genesis. Materials in this collection include scripts, programs, flyers, reviews, and publications documenting the theater's 14 seasons (1964-1978), including works by playwrights Maria Irene Fornés, H.M. "Harry" Koutoukas, Walter Hadler, Leonard Melfi, Murray Mednick, and Sam Shepard. Many of the productions documented in this collection were directed by Ralph Cook. In addition to documenting Theatre Genesis' productions, the collection also documents the financial and business operations of a theatrical space, and the growth of the off-off-Broadway movement in New York City in the 20th century.
Scope and Contents
The Stephen Facey Collection on Theatre Genesis, Inc. (dated 1964-2016) consists of materials collected by Facey documenting the history and activities of Theatre Genesis, one of the first off-off-Broadway theaters. Materials in this collection include scripts, programs, flyers, reviews, and publications documenting the theater's 14 seasons (1964-1978), including works by playwrights Maria Irene Fornés, H.M. "Harry" Koutoukas, Walter Hadler, Leonard Melfi, Murray Mednick, and Sam Shepard. Many of the productions documented in this collection were directed by Ralph Cook. The collection also contains a small amount of material Facey collected concerning the history and coverage of Theatre Genesis, as well as administrative documents for Re-Genesis, an effort to re-imagine the theatre in 1989. In addition to documenting Theatre Genesis' productions, the collection also documents the financial and business operations of a theatrical space, and the growth of the off-off-Broadway movement in New York City in the 20th century.
Arrangement
Materials are mostly in chronological order, maintaining the original order in which they were received.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Stephen Facey in December 2019; the accession number associated with this gift is 2020.003.
Biographical Note
Stephen Facey is a trustee of Movement Research, The Chocolate Factory Theater, the St. Mark's Historic Landmark Fund, and the New York Preservation Archive Project. He served as the Parish Administrator of St. Mark's Church In-the-Bowery in New York City's East Village during a period in the church's history marked by a focus on community service and cultural expansion. Facey managed the church's Arts Projects, comprised of The Film Project, The Poetry Project, the contemporary dance venue Danspace Project; and the off-off-Broadway theater Theatre Genesis. Theater Genesis produced 14 seasons and ceased operations in 1978, shortly before a major fire at St. Mark's. Facey is the former Executive Vice President of the Cathedral of St. John the Divine in New York City.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Fales Library and Special Collections, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Off Off-Broadway theater.; Experimental drama, American.; Experimental theater.; Theater -- New York (State) -- New York.; Theater -- Production and direction.; Playwriting.; East Village (New York, N.Y.); Facey, Stephen; St. Mark's Church In-the-Bowery (New York, N.Y.); Shepard, Sam, 1943-2017; Cook, Ralph; Mednick, Murray; Hadler, Walter
- Historical Information, 2013-2017 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- The Grand Inquisitor, Scene from The Brothers Karamazov Adapted by Henry M. di Suvero, Directed by Ralph Cook (Pre-Theatre Genesis), 1964-03 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Study in Color, Written by Malcolm Boyd, Directed by Woody King, 1964-07 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Cowboys and Rock Garden, Written by Sam Shepard, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1964-10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Herod and the Slaughter of the Innocents, Directed by Mark Mirsky, 1964-12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Before Breakfast in Wonderland and Cheer Up, Written by Pat Branch, Directed by Kevin O'Connor and Ralph Cook, 1965-01 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- The Drapes Come, Written by Charles Dizenzo, Directed by Robert F. Lyons, 1965-02 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Let's Get Serious and The Gate, Written by Charles Mee, Jr., Directed by Mark J. Mirsky and Anne Ohelschlager (Assistant), 1965-03 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Free, Free, Free and There's a Wall Between Us, Darling, Written by Sally Ordway, Directed by Benjamin Hiatt, 1965-04 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- The Custom Inspector in Baggy Pants, Written by Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Directed by Maurice Edwards; Chicago, Written by Sam Shepard, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1965-04 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Birdbath and Sunglasses, Written by Leonard Melfi, Directed by Ralph Cook and Richard McPhee, 1965-06 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Pussies and Rookies and FerryBoat, Written by Leonard Melfi, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1965-09 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Medea, Written by H.M. Koutoukas, Directed by Warren Finerty, 1965-09 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- The Box, Written by Murray Mednick, Directed by Lee Kissman; My Daddy is Dying, Written by Tom Sankey, Directed by Ralph Cook; Out of Town Traffic, Written by Leonard Melfi, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1965-12 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Audio Recordings of The Box and Out of Town Traffic, 1965-12 (Box 9)
- Why the Clown Never Speaks, Written by Tom Ohlson, Directed by Jack Milton; A Corner of the Morning, Written by Michael Locascio, Directed by Ken Linden; The Interrogation Room, Written by David Scott Milton, Directed by Jack Milton, 1966-02 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Degrees, Written by George Birmisa, Directed by Murray Paskin, 1966-03 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- The Pattern and The Trunk, Written by Anthony Barsha, Directed by Ralph Cook and Nick Orzel, 1966-04 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- The Mask of Zorro, Written by Murray Mednick, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1966-06 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- The Golden Screw, Written by Tom Sankey, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1966-09 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Halloween Mask, Written by David Scott, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1966-10 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- The Hearing, Written by Tony Barsha, Directed by Tony Barsha, 1966-10 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- The Key, Written by Kit Jones, Directed by Kit Jones, 1966-11 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Guideline, Written by Murray Mednick, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1966-11 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Fruit Salad, Written by Grant Duay, Directed by Tony Barsha; Smash, Written by Tony Barsha, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1967-01 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Etude, Written by Robert Howard, Directed by Amy Saltz, 1967-02 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Papyrus, Written by William Kushner, Directed by Murray Paskin; Sand, Written by Murray Mednick, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1967-03 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- The Hawk; Written by Murray Mednick, Tony Barsha, and The Keystone Company; Directed by Tony Barsha, 1967-10 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Forensic and the Navigators, Written by Sam Shepard, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1968-01 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- The Beggar's Opera, Written by Tom Sankey and Janet Day, Directed by Lee Kissman and Ralph Cook, 1968-03 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Bad Times in Bummerville, Written by Joel Oppenheimer, Directed by Tom Sankey, 1968-05 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Willie the Germ, Written by Murray Mednick, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1968-05 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Solarium, Written by Walter Hadler, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1968-06 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- The Hunter, Written by Murray Mednick, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1968-10 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
- Thirty and American Gothic, Written by Walter Hadler, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1968-11 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- H-Isolation, Written by Lee Kissman, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1969-01 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Vision of a New Body: Communal Spontaneous Vision, Written by Keystone Communal Theater Experiment in Progress, Directed by Tony Barsha, 1969-03 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Mission Beach, Written by Walter Hadler, Directed by Tony Barsha; Flight Cage, Written by Walter Hadler, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1969-04 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
- The Shadow Ripens, Written by Murray Mednick (in Collaboration with Theater Five Company of San Diego), Directed by Murray Mednick, 1969-05 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- The Waterworks at Lincoln, Written by Walter Hadler, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1969-10 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Two Plays Written by Tony Barsha, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1970-01 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- The Deer Kill, Written by Murray Mednick, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1970-04 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
- Grand Mal Crick, Written by Walter Hadler, Directed by Ralph Cook, 1971-01 (Box 3, Folder 10, Box 4, Folder 1-2)
- Mad Dog Blues, Written by Sam Shepard, Directed by Robert Glaudini, 1971-03 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
- Lesson in Dead Language, Written by Adrienne Kennedy, Directed by Gaby Rodgers, 1971-04 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- 12 Noon: Up Against the Wall Ruling Class, Written by Victor Eschbach, 1971-06 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Cartoon, Written by Murray Mednick, Directed by Walter Blood, 1971-10 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
- Country Music, Written and Directed by Michael Smith, 1971-12 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Borrowed Time, Written and Directed by Robert Glaudini, 1972-02 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Jim Town, Written by K. Kimball, Directed by Andrea Clarke, 1972-03 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Mutilitation, Written by Walter Hadler, Directed by Gaby Rodgers, 1972-05 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Bigfoot, Written by Ronald Tavel, Directed by Michael Smith, 1972-11 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Blue Bitch, Written by Sam Shepard, Directed by Murray Mednick, 1973-01 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Tango Palace, Written by Maria Irene Fornés, Directed by Michael Smith and Maria Irene Fornés, 1973-01 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Are You Lookin?, Written by Murray Mednick, Directed by Murray Mednick (Assistant Director Lee Kissman), 1973-04 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Wheeling Reds, Written and Directed by Walter Hadler, 1973-05 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- The Theory and Practice of Miss America, Written by Carolyn Lord, Executed by William Dunes, 1973-05 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Shango De Ima and Guess Who the Noisemakers Are?", Possibly Written by Jaheen Ishameli, 1973-05 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Queen of Greece, Written by Ron Tavel, Directed by CayMichael Patten, 1973-11 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Three Plays Written by Michael McClure, Directed by Rip Torn, Brenda Smiley, Phil Price, and Lee Kissman, 1973-12 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Prussian Suite, Written by Michael Smith, Possibly Directed by John Smead, 1974-03 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Habitues, Written by T.J. Camp III, Directed by Eugene Kallman, 1974-03 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Hot Peachers, The Divas of Sheridan Square (A Gay Poetry Concert), circa January 1974 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Horsemeat, a Play to See While Sipping Tea, Written by Jeff Weiss, Directed by Carlos Ricardo Martinez, 1974-04 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Malecon, Written by David Garvin, Directed by Phillip Price, 1974-05 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Typhoid Mary, or an Enema of the People, Written by Steve Shea, Directed by Edward M. Coen; First Amendment and Los Topos, Written by Third World Theater; John Hebert Workshop; McDowell in Concert, 1974-09 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Pioneer and Pro-Game, Written by Megan Terry, Directed by Harvey Tavel, 1974-10 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- City Lights; Danny Kalb, John Berenzy, Mark Abel, and Lee Bobbe, 1974-10 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Subreal: A Salute ot the Futurists by the NY Dragon Kings, Written and Directed by Daffi, circa 1975 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- The Silver Bee, Written by Walter Hadler, Directed by Daffi, circa January 1975 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- High Jolly, Written by David Garvin, Directed by Tony Barsha, 1975-02 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Against the Sun, Written by Robert Glaudini, Directed by Phillip Minor, 1975-03 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Derelict=4, Written and Directed by Blanche Medick Olaik; Eve, Written by Marcus Haufrecht, Directed by Don Blakely, 1975-04 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Poe in Person, Written by Marilyn Pomerleau, 1975-04 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Anthology and Small Scroll, Written by Meredith Monk/The House, 1975-04 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Hoe Scroll, Written by Hector Miguel Rodriguez, Directed by Richard August; Lonely Lives, Written by Hector Miguel Rodriguez, Directed by Tito Goyo, 1975-05 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Sonata, Written and Directed by Bill Duke, 1975-06 (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
- Asterian Canticles, Written and Directed by Daffi Nathansan, 1975-10 (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
- Para-Troupe (Street Theater Group) Presented by Theatre for the U.F.O. Hostages, 1975-11 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Three Plays Written by Michael MClaure, Directed by Tony Barsha and Walter Hadler, 1976-02 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Cars and Guitars, Written and Directed by Michael Winsett, 1976-04 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Auto-Destruct, Written by Jeff Wanshell, Directed by Scott Redman, 1976-11 (Box 6, Folder 13-14)
- Two Plays by Quena Company: Blue Heaven and Technocracy, Directed by Ray Barry, 1976-05 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Alto Madness, Eddie Jefferson with Richie Coles Concert, 1977-01 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Three Plays by Quena Company, Directed by Ray Barry, 1977-02 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- The Kalevala, Written by The Talking Band, 1977-01 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Bob Carroll Storytelling Performances, 1977-03 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Jo Ann in the White House, Written by Irving Stetner, 1977-03 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Theatre Genesis Goes to the Movies: A Program of Short Films, 1977-03 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- An Ordinary Evening with My Grandmother, Written and Directed by Richard Ploetz, 1977-04 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
- Three Weekends in May at Eight Mini Series: Attack of the Androgynes, Written by Stephen Policoff, Directed by Ron Nash; The Honky Tonk Piano in the All Night Cafe, Written by Stephen Policoff, Directed by Ron Nash; Metaphysical Vaudeville, Written and Directed by Rob Cassatt, 1977-05 (Box 7, Folder 8-9)
- Workshop Productions, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Lemonade, Written by James Prideux, Directed by Casey Kurtti, 1977-06 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Monday Night Play Readings: Players and Poets, 1978-01 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- The Day Roosevelt Died, Written by Barry Pritchard, Directed by Kevin O'Connor; The Ruffian on the Stair, Written by Joe Orton, Directed by Harvey Schultz, 1978-02 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Once Upon a Time a Man Came Out of the Dark and Speak/Stroll, Written and Directed by Richard Ploetz, 1978-04 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- The Truth About the Truth, Written by Harold Stuart, Directed by Norman Jacobs, 1978-04 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Contributions and Shoes, Written by Ted Shine, Directed by Edmund Cambridge, 1978-03 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- When Petulia Comes, Written by Caroline Emmons, Directed by Edward M. Cohen, 1978-05 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Immediate Family, Written by Mitchell Redman, Directed by Charles Shain, 1978-05 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Angel City, Written by Sam Shepard, Directed by Larry Sacharow, 1978-05 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Re-Genesis Administrative Documents, 1988-1989 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Lists of Plays Performed, Directors, Playwrights, Performers, 1964-1978 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- The Villager -- Ralph Lee and Poetry Project, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- New York Times -- Carlos Peliciano March, 2015 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Reverend Malcolm Boyd Obituary, 2015 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- "50 Years On: Theatre Genesis and Sam Shepard," Lee Kissman; Contemporary Theatre Review, 2014 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Newspaper Clippings about Ken Jacobs, 2013, 2016 (Box 8, Folder 11)